<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Politiconvo</title>
    <link>https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Politiconvo</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 14:08:49 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Trump administration doesn&#39;t think about American farmers</title>
      <link>https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/posts/farmers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2014 14:08:49 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/posts/farmers/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration appears incapable of understanding the broader consequences of its policy decisions. The ongoing trade war with China harms American farmers and the government&amp;rsquo;s damage control measures reflect its ineptitude. The administration began a trade dispute with Beijing without a contingency plan for retaliation on the largest U.S. export commodity to China, soybeans. The administration sabotaged efforts by American farmers to find new markets for soybeans by engaging in trade disputes with prospective importers. The administration further hurt the rural economy’s expected returns by reneging on the promise to require all domestic refineries to include soybean and corn-based ethanol in their gasoline mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-administration-lacks-foresight-and-does-not-have-a-clear-understanding-of-the-harm-its-trade-actions-are-having-on-the-economy&#34;&gt;The administration lacks foresight and does not have a clear understanding of the harm its trade actions are having on the economy.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/farmers/china_imports.png&#34; alt=&#34;Soybeans were the biggest US export to China.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When President Trump imposed sweeping tariffs on Chinese exports to the United States, the administration should have anticipated retaliation on U.S. exports to China. Soybeans were the largest U.S. export to China in 2016.
In response to the Trump administration’s tariffs, China imposed retaliatory tariffs on soybeans in April 2018. It took the U.S. government four months to introduce a $12 billion assistance fund for affected farmers. The Department of Agriculture later admitted that this amount was insufficient and increased the assistance to $16 billion in 2019 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trade-china/u-s-to-pay-farmers-up-to-16-billion-for-trade-war-losses-south-to-benefit-idUSKCN1UK2M7&#34;&gt;(but not before first suggesting that there would be no federal assistance to farmers that year).&lt;/a&gt;
The increased aid from the U.S. government reflects the extensive harm done to places like North Dakota which previously sold 70% of its soybeans to China. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trade-china-soybeans/on-the-front-lines-trade-war-sinks-north-dakota-soybean-farmers-idUSKCN1VC0ZX&#34;&gt;Agriculture is North Dakota’s largest industry, representing about 25% of its economy.&lt;/a&gt;
The damage is not limited to farmers. With shrinking sales to China, farmers are not investing in new agricultural equipment, adversely affecting manufacturers like John Deere. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/trumps-tariffs-and-bad-weather-take-toll-on-us-farmers-2019-08-17&#34;&gt;The broader rural economy is at risk.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-administration-sabotages-its-own-interests&#34;&gt;The administration sabotages its own interests.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/farmers/soya_exports.png&#34; alt=&#34;China was the biggest importer of US soybeans&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With China’s purchase of U.S. soybeans severely curtailed, U.S. farmers need to find new international customers. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trade-china-exports/china-buys-u-s-soybeans-after-declaring-ban-on-american-farm-goods-idUSKCN1VC1S9&#34;&gt;However, the U.S. government alienated potential new buyers with threats of tariffs.&lt;/a&gt; Mexico is the second largest buyer of U.S. soybeans. Instead of promoting greater U.S. soybean sales to its southern neighbor, the Trump administration engaged in a contentious trade dispute with Mexico, partly to demonstrate U.S. resolve in trade negotiations. During this time, Brazil increased its soy exports to Mexico, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/brazil-corn-mexico/mexico-buys-brazil-corn-cargo-amid-trade-spat-with-us-says-broker-idUSL8N23C5TY&#34;&gt;closing a crucial window for American farmers find new markets and offset some losses.&lt;/a&gt;
Farms in states like North Dakota can switch to crops like peas and lentils which are suitable for the local climate.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trade-india/india-to-impose-retaliatory-tariffs-on-28-us-goods-from-sunday-idUSKCN1TG0H0&#34;&gt;But India - the largest market for those commodities - currently imposes tariffs on these goods in response to U.S. tariffs on Indian commodities.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-administration-engages-in-behavior-that-unnecessarily-harms-constituents-who-are-already-under-duress&#34;&gt;The administration engages in behavior that unnecessarily harms constituents who are already under duress.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many soybean farmers facing significant financial losses, the U.S. rural economy is weak. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-farms-perdue/u-s-farm-debt-soars-to-levels-seen-during-1980s-farm-crisis-agriculture-secretary-idUSKCN1QG24Y&#34;&gt;Notably, farm debts are “historically high,” according to the Department of Agriculture.&lt;/a&gt;
Despite these vulnerabilities, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://thehill.com/policy/energy-environment/458339-farmers-say-trump-broke-promise-on-ethanol-with-waivers-to&#34;&gt;administration decided to break its promise with corn and soybean farmers&lt;/a&gt; to enforce the purchase of corn-based ethanol and soybean-based biofuels by small refineries for their gasoline mix. This decision on gasoline mix appears to have been driven by the administration’s desire to appeal to the oil industry &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-07-10/trump-defends-refinery-waivers-by-noting-expanded-ethanol-sales&#34;&gt;without considering how it may impact an already-vulnerable sector.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion-the-trump-administration-does-not-spend-sufficient-time-considering-the-secondary-consequences-of-its-decisions-leaving-the-american-people-exposed-to-foreseeable-shocks&#34;&gt;Conclusion: The Trump administration does not spend sufficient time considering the secondary consequences of its decisions, leaving the American people exposed to foreseeable shocks.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not address whether the administration should or should not confront China over technology theft, patent infringement, national-security concerns, anti-dumping, and other unfair trade practices. We ask whether the U.S. administration considers the consequences of its tactics on domestic constituencies.
If the administration does consider the consequences, we must ask why it engaged in trade policies that make it harder for farmers to diversify from the Chinese market. &lt;em&gt;This is especially perplexing since the farmers’ inability to offset losses in China strengthens Beijing’s negotiating position.&lt;/em&gt;
This memo also does not seek to adjudicate whether or not it is economical or useful to include ethanol in gasoline - but rather to ask whether this was the most appropriate time to address the issue when the rural economy desperately needed more people to acquire agricultural goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The administration&amp;rsquo;s negligent, or inept, policy prescriptions harm Americans it ran on serving.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
