<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Washington Dispatch</title>
    <link>https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Washington Dispatch</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2019 14:08:49 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Trump administration doesn&#39;t think about American farmers</title>
      <link>https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/posts/farmers/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2019 14:08:49 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/posts/farmers/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration appears incapable of understanding the broader consequences of its policy decisions. The ongoing trade war with China harms American farmers and the government&amp;rsquo;s damage control measures reflect its ineptitude. The administration began a trade dispute with Beijing without a contingency plan for retaliation on the largest U.S. export commodity to China, soybeans. The administration sabotaged efforts by American farmers to find new markets for soybeans by engaging in trade disputes with prospective importers. The administration further hurt the rural economy’s expected returns by reneging on the promise to require all domestic refineries to include soybean and corn-based ethanol in their gasoline mix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-administration-lacks-foresight-and-does-not-have-a-clear-understanding-of-the-harm-its-trade-actions-are-having-on-the-economy&#34;&gt;The administration lacks foresight and does not have a clear understanding of the harm its trade actions are having on the economy.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/farmers/china_imports.png&#34; alt=&#34;Soybeans were the biggest US export to China.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When President Trump imposed sweeping tariffs on Chinese exports to the United States, the administration should have anticipated retaliation on U.S. exports to China. Soybeans were the largest U.S. export to China in 2016.
In response to the Trump administration’s tariffs, China imposed retaliatory tariffs on soybeans in April 2018. It took the U.S. government four months to introduce a $12 billion assistance fund for affected farmers. The Department of Agriculture later admitted that this amount was insufficient and increased the assistance to $16 billion in 2019 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trade-china/u-s-to-pay-farmers-up-to-16-billion-for-trade-war-losses-south-to-benefit-idUSKCN1UK2M7&#34;&gt;(but not before first suggesting that there would be no federal assistance to farmers that year).&lt;/a&gt;
The increased aid from the U.S. government reflects the extensive harm done to places like North Dakota which previously sold 70% of its soybeans to China. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trade-china-soybeans/on-the-front-lines-trade-war-sinks-north-dakota-soybean-farmers-idUSKCN1VC0ZX&#34;&gt;Agriculture is North Dakota’s largest industry, representing about 25% of its economy.&lt;/a&gt;
The damage is not limited to farmers. With shrinking sales to China, farmers are not investing in new agricultural equipment, adversely affecting manufacturers like John Deere. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.marketwatch.com/story/trumps-tariffs-and-bad-weather-take-toll-on-us-farmers-2019-08-17&#34;&gt;The broader rural economy is at risk.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-administration-sabotages-its-own-interests&#34;&gt;The administration sabotages its own interests.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/farmers/soya_exports.png&#34; alt=&#34;China was the biggest importer of US soybeans&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With China’s purchase of U.S. soybeans severely curtailed, U.S. farmers need to find new international customers. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trade-china-exports/china-buys-u-s-soybeans-after-declaring-ban-on-american-farm-goods-idUSKCN1VC1S9&#34;&gt;However, the U.S. government alienated potential new buyers with threats of tariffs.&lt;/a&gt; Mexico is the second largest buyer of U.S. soybeans. Instead of promoting greater U.S. soybean sales to its southern neighbor, the Trump administration engaged in a contentious trade dispute with Mexico, partly to demonstrate U.S. resolve in trade negotiations. During this time, Brazil increased its soy exports to Mexico, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/brazil-corn-mexico/mexico-buys-brazil-corn-cargo-amid-trade-spat-with-us-says-broker-idUSL8N23C5TY&#34;&gt;closing a crucial window for American farmers find new markets and offset some losses.&lt;/a&gt;
Farms in states like North Dakota can switch to crops like peas and lentils which are suitable for the local climate.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-trade-india/india-to-impose-retaliatory-tariffs-on-28-us-goods-from-sunday-idUSKCN1TG0H0&#34;&gt;But India - the largest market for those commodities - currently imposes tariffs on these goods in response to U.S. tariffs on Indian commodities.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-administration-engages-in-behavior-that-unnecessarily-harms-constituents-who-are-already-under-duress&#34;&gt;The administration engages in behavior that unnecessarily harms constituents who are already under duress.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With many soybean farmers facing significant financial losses, the U.S. rural economy is weak. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reuters.com/article/us-usa-farms-perdue/u-s-farm-debt-soars-to-levels-seen-during-1980s-farm-crisis-agriculture-secretary-idUSKCN1QG24Y&#34;&gt;Notably, farm debts are “historically high,” according to the Department of Agriculture.&lt;/a&gt;
Despite these vulnerabilities, the &lt;a href=&#34;https://thehill.com/policy/energy-environment/458339-farmers-say-trump-broke-promise-on-ethanol-with-waivers-to&#34;&gt;administration decided to break its promise with corn and soybean farmers&lt;/a&gt; to enforce the purchase of corn-based ethanol and soybean-based biofuels by small refineries for their gasoline mix. This decision on gasoline mix appears to have been driven by the administration’s desire to appeal to the oil industry &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-07-10/trump-defends-refinery-waivers-by-noting-expanded-ethanol-sales&#34;&gt;without considering how it may impact an already-vulnerable sector.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion-the-trump-administration-does-not-spend-sufficient-time-considering-the-secondary-consequences-of-its-decisions-leaving-the-american-people-exposed-to-foreseeable-shocks&#34;&gt;Conclusion: The Trump administration does not spend sufficient time considering the secondary consequences of its decisions, leaving the American people exposed to foreseeable shocks.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This does not address whether the administration should or should not confront China over technology theft, patent infringement, national-security concerns, anti-dumping, and other unfair trade practices. We ask whether the U.S. administration considers the consequences of its tactics on domestic constituencies.
If the administration does consider the consequences, we must ask why it engaged in trade policies that make it harder for farmers to diversify from the Chinese market. &lt;em&gt;This is especially perplexing since the farmers’ inability to offset losses in China strengthens Beijing’s negotiating position.&lt;/em&gt;
This memo also does not seek to adjudicate whether or not it is economical or useful to include ethanol in gasoline - but rather to ask whether this was the most appropriate time to address the issue when the rural economy desperately needed more people to acquire agricultural goods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The administration&amp;rsquo;s negligent, or inept, policy prescriptions harm Americans it ran on serving.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Separation</title>
      <link>https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/posts/separation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2018 14:08:49 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://bwarren2.github.io/politiconvo/posts/separation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I want to write a different, conservative take on Trump&amp;rsquo;s family separation policy.  I&amp;rsquo;ll presume that Trump&amp;rsquo;s aims are fundamentally correct, i.e.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;illegal immigration is a very serious problem of national security importance to the US;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;that illegal immigrants merit no expectations of good treatment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two assumptions short-circuit most of the criticism lobbed by liberals at the policy.  (For example, &amp;ldquo;but this is cruel!&amp;rdquo; falls down because illegal immigrants merit no expectations of good treatment.) So: with these assumptions, was the Trump administration&amp;rsquo;s family separation policy an effective means to pursue conservative goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Briefly: no.  Because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it did not stick, was unlikely ever to stick, and was pursued at the expense of alternatives that might have stuck;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it was more expensive than other, more durable alternatives;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;poor administration left children in limbo, resulting in their permanent entry to the US;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it undermined the expectations of stable, constant rule of law&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we can reason by analogy.  The Trump administration was trying to effect lasting change in US immigration patterns, with the key word being &lt;em&gt;lasting&lt;/em&gt;.  A policy that is immediately struck down or recanted under extreme pressure is like a crash diet that only lasts a week: it doesn&amp;rsquo;t effect lasting change, and is mostly a waste of time, especially compared to responsible choices that &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; produce lasting change.  In a diet that might exercising a little; in immigration, it might have been detaining parents and children together, more often, and longer, publicizing that surrendering at the border is just an express bus to a holding prison and deportation.  Instead of releasing people pending trial, this would have made surrendering pointless; why cross the border to go to prison and then back where you came from, rather than just not going at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This route has the key benefit of being much more likely to stick than a family separation policy.  The optics of separating preteen children and toddlers from parents are obviously worse than families in holding pens together, and are much more likely to produce backlash.  Instead of showing slightly more deterrence for three years, this policy would have been a permanent deterrent for multiple years to come, making a bigger dent in the immigration problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the second reason regarding cost, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trump_administration_family_separation_policy#Fiscal_costs_and_diversion_of_resources&#34;&gt;holding kids with parents is also about &lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt; the cost of holding them separately.&lt;/a&gt;. This is no small expense; the administration was &lt;a href=&#34;https://time.com/5316722/nonprofit-paid-458-million-trump-administration-detain-migrant-children-family-separation/&#34;&gt;reported paying half a billion dollars to a nonprofit to keep children in custody&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://edition.cnn.com/2018/09/20/politics/hhs-shifting-money-cancer-aids-immigrant-children/index.html&#34;&gt;a quarter billion dollars coming from cancer research, HIV/AIDS programs, and more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely there must be some benefit to a policy that is more expensive and shorter lived than other options, no?  Actually, this policy probably resulted in &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; illegal children entering the US than a simple &amp;ldquo;jail with parents&amp;rdquo; alternative. The third reason this policy was a problem is that administrative failure effectively stranded illegal children without their parents, leaving them wards of the US government.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usatoday.com/story/news/nation/2018/07/24/immigration-parents-may-have-been-deported-without-kids/824904002/&#34;&gt;At least 450 parents have been deported without their children&lt;/a&gt;, a display of bureacratic incompetence that is much more difficult to achieve when the parents and children are kept together.  With a goal of keeping illegals out of the country, this fact represents the most salient failure of the policy: it actually &lt;em&gt;increased&lt;/em&gt; the number of illegals in the country compared to obvious alternatives by leaving the children in permanent US residence!  &lt;a href=&#34;https://thehill.com/policy/international/americas/410653-ap-migrant-children-may-be-adopted-after-parents-are-deported&#34;&gt;Some of them are even being adopted into the US&lt;/a&gt;.  What is the point of a policy to keep immigrants out that lets more &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a policy that lurches into and out of existence has intangible harms beyond people and money.  Institutions and the rule of law undergird our society, framing expectations about stable, predictable, and reliable government action.  How will groups that work with the United States respond to such hectic policymaking, implementation, and reversal?  Why should they rely on the administration&amp;rsquo;s statements, or even their policies, lasting more than a couple months?  How much less is the word of the government worth when the words of administrations don&amp;rsquo;t match their actions, or even their own words in the same week?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking on Face the Nation on June 17, Senator Susan Collins said that the Secretary of Homeland Security Kirstjen Nielsen had testified before the Senate that asylum seekers with families would not be separated if they presented themselves at a legal port of entry, &amp;ldquo;Yet, there are numerous credible media accounts showing that exactly that is happening, and the administration needs to put an end to that right off.&amp;rdquo;[9] Later in the day Nielsen tweeted: &amp;ldquo;We do not have a policy of separating families at the border. Period.&amp;rdquo; - &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trump_administration_family_separation_policy#Homeland_Security_Secretary_Kirstjen_Nielsen&#34;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration&amp;rsquo;s family separation policy was more expensive and less effective than imprisoning children with parents, and it actually leaked more children into the country through sheer ineptitude.  The United States burned credibility defending or denying the existence of a fleeting, ineffective program. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.politico.com/story/2018/06/20/full-text-trump-executive-order-family-separations-transcript-658639&#34;&gt;The Trump administration&amp;rsquo;s executive order reversing the policy&lt;/a&gt; would have been better issued immediately after the policy was implemented.  Or better: the administration could have hired someone better at pursuing conservative goals and handed the job to them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
